Guide to the Arvind Krishna Mehrotra papers, 1960-2014.
Mehrotra, Arvind Krishna papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Arvind Krishna Mehrotra papers, 1960-2014.
8511
Mehrotra, Arvind Krishna,
6.1 Cubic Feet.
Correspondence, publications.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes correspondence, published material and some manuscripts.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Mehrotra is a 20th century modernist poet of India, an editor, translator and literary critic. Along with Adil Jussawalla, Mehrotra formed the Clearing House, which published the works of leading figures such as Arun Kolatkar, Gieve Patel, and Dilip Chitre, among others. The "Bombay Poets" were not strictly confined to Bombay/Mumbai, but included figures such as AK Ramanujan, who lived in the United States.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes correspondence, published material and some manuscripts.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Mehrotra, Arvind Krishna, 1947-; Clearing House.
Subjects:
India -- In literature.; Indic literature (English) -- History and criticism.
Form and Genre Terms:
Poetry; Criticism, interpretation, etc.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SEPARATED MATERIAL
The following publications are cataloged individually:
De Souza, Eunice. Learn from the almond leaf. Mumbai: Poetrywala, 2016. Signed by the author. Asia Rare PR9499.3.D43 L53
Kolatakara, Aruna. The boatride: a poem. [India?]: [publisher not identified], [between 1960 and 1969?] Signed by the author. Asia Rare PR9499.3.K57 B62
Mehrotra, Arvind Krishna. Bharatmata: a prayer. [India?]: [publisher not identified], [between 1960 and 1969?] Asia Rare PR9499.3.M38 B35
Mehrotra, Arvind Krishna. Distance in statute miles. [Photocopy of original with imprint Bombay: Clearing House, 1982] Asia Rare PR9499.3.M38 D5 1982a
RELATED MATERIALS
Related material located in collection #8519, Adil Jussawalla papers.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Arvind Krishna Mehrotra Manuscripts, Drafts, Personal Materials and Reviews
Series II. Publications
Series III. Other Authors and Miscellaneous
Series IV. Correspondence
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Arvind Krishna Mehrotra Manuscripts, Drafts, Personal Materials and Reviews
  - Loose Sheets, Ezra 1 and 2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Damn you/Ezra contributions (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Including Agha Shahid Ali, letters from Adil (new writing in India), Tornado #5 (expenses), letters from US Poets
  - Review clippings, Clearing House, 1977-1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Early writings, late 1960s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Drafts and manuscripts, late 1970s (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Reviews of Damn you/ Ezra (Box 1, Folder 1)
    In Century (1966), Poetry India (1967), Manhattan Review(1966-1967)
  - Contributions to other US, UK, and Indian magazines (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
    Includes NPW/Kruti and Tornado #4, Bombay Duck
  - TLS with poems, 1978, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Poems, manuscripts and drafts, 2000-2013 (Box 1, Folder 5-9)
  - Songs of Kabir MSS and drafts, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 12-15)
  - Shakti Chattopadhyay (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - History of Indian Literature in English file (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - History of Indian Literature in English initial stages, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - History of Indian Literature in English correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Looking for A.K. Ramanujan clippings, notes and drafts (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Iowa materials, bound, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - DH Law review essay materials (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - The Transfiguring Places drafts of poems (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - MSS drafts of poems that first appear under New Poems in Collected Poems, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Copies of The Nation, MPT (17), Romanian Bulletin, all with AK Mehrotra poems or translations; Penguin News with announcement of Adil Jussawalla's "New Writing in India". (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - The Picador Book of Modern Indian Literature publishing information, photocopy with corrections of "The Emperor Has No Clothes"., 2000 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - MSS of the Absent Traveller with AK Ramanujan's corrections/suggestions in pencil, with letters from Selby and Ramanujan, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - MSS of the Absent Traveller, notes and drafts, with letter from Selby, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - The Absent Traveller notes and drafts, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Mehrotra's Curriculum Vitae, book selection photocopies, materials for a grant/fellowship that never came through (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - The Transfiguring Places proofs, drafts, letters to Ravi Dayal (Box 4, Folder 8-10)
  - Clippings and notes related to History of Indian Literature in English (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Includes Prathibha Nandakumar letter and photocopies of AK Ramanujan letters/poems to her.
  - Articles and reviews received from Adil Jussawalla, including letters from Jussawalla (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - AK Mehrortra early chapbooks: "Woodcuts on Paper" and "Pomes, Poemes, Poemas", 1967, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - List of early publications, early letters to publishers, translations of poems in German, 1965-1976 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Three early Mehrortra essays, one unpublished;, international writing program Iowa presentations and materials; Center for New Performing Arts Iowa publications, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Manuscripts, 1973-1977, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Distance in Statute Miles typescript, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Kabir beginnings, including signed copy of Robert Bly's chapbook "The Fish in the Water is Not Thirsty (1971), and poster for the Indian edition of "Songs of Kabir" (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - "All to Remember", unpublished typescript of Amit Rai (1948-1966) collected poems, prose, and letters edited by Mehrortra., 1971 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    Rai was one of the three editors of Damn You.
  - The Absent Traveller drafts (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Making books, including final MSS of Distance to Statute Miles, 1971-1982 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - History of Indian Literature in English (Box 5, Folder 3-5)
  - After Maluk MS, Paper Aeroplane, Poems from the goof surrealist MS, Partial recall essay, Nirala MS, letters from Helsa, Gulam Sheikh, the Yaddo file, GRE scores (Box 5, Folder 6-8)
  - Miscellaneous press books and manuscripts (Box 6, Folder 10-13)
  - Address book, notebook (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Genesis copies and notebook, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Two copies of Genesis, Mehrotra’s first “book,” produced when he was 17 (one bound, one unbound); small notebook with Siva on cover—poems, pieces, doodles.
  - News clippings, 1970-1972 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Certificates, 1962-1963 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Series II. Publications
  - "Imprint" Magazine, with reviews, February, May 1987 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Debonair" Magazine, 1981-1990 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Joseph Bruchac publications (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Flow, Indian Mountain and Other Poems, The Road to Black Mountain
  - Miscellaneous small publications (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
    Including Row With Your Hair, Troll Songs, Zuk, Cold Mountain Press, Nights of Naomi, Let the Wild Rumpus Start, Wondering Where You Are, Westbeth Poetry
  - "The Dolphin with the Revolver in its Teeth", "Shaded Room" (1), "Quark" (1967), "Maelstro" (1967), "Earthword" (1971), "Bear" (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "The Beauties of Travel", "The Poor Devil Eire", "Llamas Allmanac", "Margins" (1975) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Journal of South Asian Literature (1974), Mahfil (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Toothpaste", "The Very First Love Letter" (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "Red Crow", 1972, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - University of Tampa, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "The Nation", with Grace Shulman's poems and correspondence, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Keeper's Voice", 1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Ole!" with letter from Doug Blazeg, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Klacto, Suction, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Kolkata du Haazar", 1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Indian Horizons", 1985 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Contra '66" full set (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Gulam Sheikh catalogue, and letter, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Vrishchik, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Saint Botolph's Review" #2 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Weissbort's 'Home' (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Black Graphics International" (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - British and US little magazines, including "Intrepid" special issue on India (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
  - TriQuarterly 37: Going to Heaven, with a letter from Elliott Anderson, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - "Town Poems" by Ashok Chopra, an Ezra-Fakir publications, and single copy of Ezra #2 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - "Damn You" issues 1-6 and "An Odd Thing" by Anil Saari, a Damn You press publications (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - "Three" by Bogomil Gjuzel, translated by Mehrotra, Ezra-Fakir press, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - "Ezra" 1, 3-5; Fakir; "Bharatmata"; "Concrete poetry" loose sheets; twelve poems from the "Good Surrealist"; Clearing House cards and flyers (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - "Salt Lick" materials (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous programs and small press books (Box 6, Folder 10-15)
- Series III. Other Authors and Miscellaneous
  - Agha Shahid Ali, Keki Daruwalla, Dilip Chitre clippings and letters (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Saklatvala and Kabraji xerox copies (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Dom Moraes, Arun Kolatkar, and notes on Jejuri (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Adil Jussawalla, Manohar Shetty (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Eunice de Souza, Vikram Seth (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Jayanta Mahapatra poems, clippings, and letters (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Nissim Ezekiel xeroxes, reviews, Edinburgh interlude, note on Ezekiel (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Arun Kolatkar unpublished MSS of his novel 'Royan' (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Nile" poems by Tomaz Salamun, autographed typescript, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Arun's 'Sarpa Satra', Adil's poems (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Copy of Adil Jussawalla "Land's End" with his corrections and letter; photocopies of Jussawalla's "Trying to Say Goodbye" and "The Right Kind of Dog"; copies of Dilip Chitre chapbooks; Mehrotra's notes on translation and unpublished interview with Vijay Kumar (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Michael Lally items (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Arun Kolatkar writing, 1964, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    In English, an unsewn manuscript signature of notes, poems, and sketches (1960s?); in Marathi, two manuscript signatures of poetry, hand-written and water-stained; Signed typescript of Jejuri in English, 1974.
- Series IV. Correspondence
  - Family Letters (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Including letters from Ved Mehra and Palash Krishna Mehrotra; letter from Arun Kolatkar's nephew
  - Correspondence to Leonard S. Marcus, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous letters, 1990s (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Including letters from Adil, Manohar, Jeet, Ranjit, Allan, Pankaj (postcard about first impressions of the US)
  - Correspondence, 1989-1999 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Letters from writers: Adil Jussawalla, Shetty, Jayanta, Daniel Weissbort, Timothy Hyman, and others (Box 5, Folder 10-11)
  - Letters from friends and academics, including Bruce King, Martha Selby, and others, 1980s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 12-14)
  - Letters from Adil, Shetty, Allan Sealy, Weissbort and others (Box 6, Folder 1-6)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 6, Folder 7-9)
  - Correspondence, Undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Oxford University Press Correspondence, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Three photocopied letters from Rukum Advani of OUP soliciting permission on any terms to publish Arun Kolatkar’s work.
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Books - cataloged individually in the Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections.
de Souza, Eunice. Learn from the Almond Leaf, 2016. Signed.
Mehrotra, Arvind Krishna. Bharatmata: a prayer, 1967. Offprint from Poetry India.
Kolatkar, Arun. The Boatride, circa 1960s. Signed self-made book, with experimental paper treatment.
Kolatkar, Arun. The Policeman, 1969. 1st edition.